Guide to the Deane Keller Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Deane Keller papers
1910-1983
1943-1975
MS 1685
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
24.25
The papers consist of correspondence, files on portrait clients, military documents and photographs from Deane Keller's service during World War II, teaching files, and miscellaneous writings, documenting Keller's professional and personal lives.
Keller, Deane, 1901-1992
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Deane Keller, 1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in six series: I. Personal, 1911-1980. II. Correspondence, 1910-1983. III. World War II, 1940-1960 (inclusive), 1943-1946 (bulk). IV. Professional, 1914-1980. V. Writings, 1936-1978. VI. Teaching, 1930-1968.
Scope and Contents
The papers include extensive information on the professional and personal lives of Deane Keller. The collection details the practice, clientele and income of a professional portrait painter in the twentieth century. Documentation of Keller's career provides valuable commentary on the coexistence of traditional and avant garde art forms. It also illustrates the continuing demand for painted portraits in an age of mechanical reproduction, when photographs provided an affordable, but not always utilized, alternative. The collection also includes extensive records of Allied attempts to protect Italian art objects during World War II, dating from Keller's service as a Fine Arts officer attached to the Fifth Army in Italy. Visual and textual materials document Keller's activities and the fate of specific monuments and collections. These materials on the German and Allied struggle to control and preserve Italian artistic patrimony vividly illustrate the cultural and propagandistic importance of museums and art objects in Western culture. Keller's life as a soldier is described in his extensive wartime correspondence. Family relationships are also documented through correspondence. Of particular interest is that between Keller and his father, Albert, the eminent Yale professor of sociology dedicated to continuing the work of William Graham Sumner. These letters document the father-son relationship as well as the elder Keller's political and academic opinions.
Biographical / Historical
Deane Keller was born in New Haven, Connecticut, on December 14, 1901. He was the son of Caroline Gussman Keller and Albert Galloway Keller, Yale Professor of Sociology and disciple of William Graham Sumner. Keller grew up in New Haven and received his high school education at the Taft School. He graduated from Yale University in 1923 with a degree in history and science. Despite the protests of his father, Keller went on to pursue his true interest in art at the Yale School of Fine Arts, earning a B.F.A. in 1926. Keller was awarded a Prix de Rome in the subsequent year on the basis of his submission of an allegorical painting, and spent three years studying at the American Academy in Rome. He began his lifelong career as a teacher at the Yale School of the Fine Arts in 1929 as an Instructor of Painting and Drawing. In 1938 he married Katherine P. Hall. They had two sons, Deane G. and William.
Keller's forty year career teaching life drawing and traditional painting techniques to Yale art students was interrupted only by his service in World War II. Keller served as a Fine Arts officer attached to the Fifth Army in Italy from 1943 to 1946. His duties as a Fine Arts officer were twofold: to locate and safeguard art treasures, and to coordinate emergency restoration of damaged monuments, churches and museums. For example, he was often first on the scene at places like the Campo Santo, Pisa, where he directed efforts to preserve frescoes badly damaged by American artillery. Keller also supervised the return of famed artworks taken from the Uffizi Gallery, Florence, by German forces. For his efforts during the war he was awarded the United States Legion of Merit, the Member of the British Empire medal, and the Order of St. John the Lateran from the Vatican.
Keller's second career was that of a portrait painter. At Yale he was known as the "unofficial portraitist of the Yale faculty." At his death he had completed over 160 portrait commissions for the university, including faculty, corporation board members, and two presidents. Keller also painted a wide range of portraits for clients outside Yale; some of his famous subjects included Senator Robert Taft, Governor John Lodge, and Presidents William Howard Taft and Herbert Hoover.
Keller returned to his position as a professor of painting and drawing at the Yale School of Arts in 1946. During the 1950s and 1960s Keller was a staunch supporter of traditional techniques in the face of the modern arts movements headed by Joseph Albers, chairman of the department of design at the Yale School of Art. Keller retired from teaching in 1970, but continued to paint portraits. Of his own work he said, "I'm not a modern painter at all. [My work] is naturalistic. Some would call it realistic, but it's not necessarily that. All painting is interpretation." Deane Keller died in Hamden, Connecticut, on April 12, 1992, at the age of 91.
Art treasures in war; Art, Italian -- Conservation and restoration; Portrait painting, American; Soldiers -- United States -- History -- 20th Century; Florence (Italy) -- History -- 1860-1945; Italy -- Description and travel; Italy -- History -- Allied occupation, 1943-1947; Italy -- History -- German occupation, 1943-1945; Naples (Italy); Rome (Italy) -- History -- 1870-1945; Photographs; Keller, Albert Galloway, 1874-1956; Keller, Deane, 1901-1992; Galleria degli Uffizi; Museo nazionale del Bargello (Florence, Italy); Palazzo Pitti; Yale University. School of Art
- Personal, 1911-1980; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Personal is comprised of various biographical resources on Keller, arranged alphabetically. The materials in this series provide an introduction to Keller's life and work. Awards and citations include decorations awarded to Keller for his service in World War II, as well as honorary degrees and prizes in art competitions. Biographical contains obituaries, memorials, and newspaper articles summarizing Keller's career. Photographs provide images of Keller and his family. Images under the heading "Rome" are an excellent record of Keller as a young artist at the American Academy. World War II newspaper clippings document Keller's career as a Fine Arts officer for the United States Army.
  - Awards and citations, 1924-1925, 1945-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    See also: box 53, folder 1
  - Biographical, 1925, 1942, 1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Education
    - Elementary school, 1911-1914, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - High school [Taft School], 1917-1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Yale University, 1918-1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Financial records, 1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interview [on portrait of Herbert Hoover], 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs
    - Positives
      - Artists and artworks, 1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Places
        - General, 1927, 1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - Rome [American Academy], 1922-1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - People
        - Keller, Deane, 1953-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
          See also: box 53, folder 2
        - Keller family, 1960, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
        - Others
          - Identified, 1960-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
          - Unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Negatives [unidentified], undated (Box 2, Folder 15 - 16)
  - Poems [composed in honor of Keller], 1936, 1960-1964, 1971, 1973, 1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - World War II [clippings on Keller's art rescue efforts]
    - English, 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 18 - 19)
    - German, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Italian, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1910-1983; Series II
  Correspondence is comprised of two sections: Alphabetical, arranged by correspondent's last name, and Chronological. The arrangement maintains Keller's filing system. This series contains a mix of personal and professional material spanning Keller's lifetime, from his first time away from home at boarding school to his lengthy career at Yale and his retirement years. Alphabetical includes his most faithful and voluminous correspondents, while Chronological provides an evolving portrait of his lifestyle and career.
  Particularly notable in the Alphabetical section is Keller's sizable correspondence with his family while stationed abroad during World War II. Though wartime censorship prevented Keller from discussing his work, the letters, especially those between Keller and his wife, Katherine, provide extensive testimony to the stresses and daily conditions of the time. Keller's letters to his young son, Deane G., also include a number of remarkable sketches meant to amuse a child, including images of soldiers, Army quarters and Italian landscapes. Correspondence with Charles Bernholz, Keller's assistant and photographer in the Fine Arts section, testifies to the close personal friendship between the men and includes reminiscences of their art rescue efforts.
  Alphabetical also contains letters pertaining to Keller's career as a professional portrait painter. Correspondence with Portraits, Inc. documents Keller's longtime association with a New York City firm that matched painters with clients. (Correspondence dealing with specific portrait commissions can also be found in the Client Files in Series IV. Professional). These letters reveal much about Keller's clientele, business practices, and the travails of portrait painting. Discussions of Keller's portraits can also be found in the correspondence with Alan Steinert, along with personal news, reminiscences, and commentary on Yale affairs of the 1950s and 1960s.
  Chronological encompasses a broad range of correspondence for the years 1910-1983. It includes personal correspondence with family, friends and Yale classmates, letters on university and Yale School of Art business, and exchanges with portrait clients.
  - Alphabetical
    - A-B, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 1 - 2)
    - Bergin, Thomas, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Bernholz, Charles, 1944-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Brooks, John, 1958-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - C-K, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 6 - 13)
    - Keller, Albert G. [father]
      - Incoming, 1916-1957, undated (Box 4, Folder 14 - 19)
      - Outgoing, 1921-1929 (Box 4, Folder 20 - 23)
    - Keller, Albert G. and Caroline [parents], 1942-1945 (Box 5, Folder 24 - 28)
    - Keller, Caroline [mother], 1916-1946, undated (Box 5, Folder 29 - 31)
    - Keller, Caroline [sister], 1941-1945 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Keller, Deane G. [son], 1943-1946 (Box 6, Folder 33 - 34)
    - Keller, Katherine [wife]
      - Incoming, 1943-1946, undated (Box 6, Folder 35 - 41)
      - Outgoing
        - 1943-1944 (Box 7, Folder 42 - 51)
        - 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 52 - 60)
    - L, 1943-1946 (Box 9, Folder 61)
    - Lawrie, Lee and Mildred, 1959-1964 (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - M-N, 1943-1946 (Box 9, Folder 63 - 64)
    - Newhall, Richard, 1970-1972 (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - O-P, 1943-1946 (Box 9, Folder 66 - 67)
    - Portraits, Incorporated, 1948-1956 (Box 9, Folder 68)
    - R, 1943-1946 (Box 9, Folder 69)
    - Rathbone, Dr. M, 1973-1975 (Box 9, Folder 70)
    - S, 1943-1946 (Box 9, Folder 71)
    - Steinert, Alan, 1947-1969 (Box 9, Folder 72 - 73)
    - T, 1943-1946 (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - Trust Company Bank, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - V, 1943-1946 (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - Chronological
    - 1910-1932 (Box 10, Folder 77 - 84)
    - 1933-1947 (Box 11, Folder 85 - 96)
    - 1948-1954 (Box 12, Folder 97 - 105)
    - 1955-1960, [195-] (Box 13, Folder 106 - 112)
    - 1961-1966 (Box 14, Folder 113 - 118)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 15, Folder 119 - 123)
    - 1970, [197-] (Box 16, Folder 124 - 129)
    - 1971-1974 (Box 17, Folder 130 - 137)
    - 1975-1983, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 138 - 146)
- World War II, 1940-1960 (inclusive), 1943-1946 (bulk); Series III
  World War II is comprised of six sections, arranged alphabetically: Fifth Army - History of the Italian Campaign; Manuscripts, Fine Arts and Archives; Memorabilia; Notebooks; Photographs; and Wartime Publications. This series provides extensive official, personal, and photographic documentation of Keller's service as a Fine Arts officer attached to the Fifth Army in Italy. Particularly notable are the extensive written and photographic resources on the fate of Italian monuments and artworks during the war, including damage reports, records of restoration efforts, and first-hand accounts of the return of stolen paintings.
  Fifth Army - History of the Italian campaign files contain materials for an official history of that campaign which Keller co-wrote with Rock Ferris. Keller was chiefly responsible for writing about the Allied Military Government, an institution set up to maintain order and provide humanitarian aid in newly liberated Italian territory. An incomplete manuscript and draft chapters provide detailed accounts of the activities of the United States Fifth Army and the Allied Military Government in Italy, as do the associated source materials, which include personal statements and official records.
  Manuscripts, Fine Arts and Archives (a subdivision of the Allied Military Government) documents both German and Allied interest in the fate of cultural treasures in the midst of war. First-hand accounts of Keller's activities are provided in "Duties of a Fine Arts Officer" and "Sectional History - Fine Arts." Correspondence and Reports extensively document Keller's movements and decisions during his art rescue efforts. There are also numerous official publications intended to aid Fine Arts officers in identifying and protecting monuments and artworks. They include the American Defense-Harvard Group lists of monuments, official policies on preservation and restoration work, and lists of protected artworks and monuments. These latter documents are useful for the researcher interested in tracing a particular city, monument, or art object during the war years.
  Keller's notebooks are arranged chronologically, with one folder arranged numerically according to his own labels. They contain extensive, but often illegible, field notes on the status of various monuments and restoration efforts attempted. Notebooks for May-July 1945 include comments on the handling of stolen Florentine art treasures.
  The Photographs section is comprised of two sub-sections: Envelopes and Loose. Keller's labels and groupings are maintained in the Envelopes section, while Loose images have been arranged by subject. Taken as a whole, these images constitute a remarkable visual record of the Italian peninsula during the Second World War, from snapshots of citizens, soldiers, and topography, to extensive detailing of the damage and movement of monuments and artworks. The photographs in the Envelopes section were taken primarily by Charles Bernholz, Keller's friend and associate during the war. Bernholz was a trained photographer authorized to document Keller's work as a Fine Arts officer. The prints from Bernholz' negatives were developed in the 1970s. Folder titles are derived from Keller's labels on the developer's envelopes. Because they were created some years after the fact, and applied only to the envelopes and not to specific images, these labels can be somewhat misleading. They offer a rough guide to the content of each folder, but since folders often contain subjects not indicated by the label, additional subject matter has been indicated in brackets wherever possible. The Loose sub-section contains photographs from a variety of sources, including the United States Army, Italian and German photography firms, and a host of unknown photographers.
  Wartime publications include materials in English, German, and Italian, such as Army magazines, American and European newspapers, and guidebooks to Italy. Clippings from American newspapers concerning Keller's military career can also be found in Series I. Personal. World War II.
  - "Charley and the Captain" [notes for a history of Keller's and Charles Bernholz' service in WWII, unpublished], undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Fifth Army - History of the Italian Campaign
    - Correspondence, 1945-1955, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript
      - Incomplete, undated (Box 19, Folder 3 - 4)
      - Chapters
        - Agriculture, undated (Box 19, Folder 5)
        - Alto Adige, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
        - Campaigns, undated (Box 19, Folder 7 - 8)
        - Communications, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
        - Fine arts, undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
        - Partisans, undated (Box 19, Folder 11)
        - Public safety, undated (Box 19, Folder 12)
        - Public welfare, undated (Box 19, Folder 13)
        - Red Cross, undated (Box 19, Folder 14)
        - Refugees, undated (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - Source material
      - Allied Military Government accounts, undated (Box 20, Folder 16)
      - Clippings, 1943-1945, undated (Box 20, Folder 17)
      - Division fact sheets, 1945 (Box 20, Folder 18)
      - "Eighth Army History", undated (Box 20, Folder 19)
      - Finance, 1945, undated (Box 20, Folder 20)
      - French Corps notes, undated (Box 20, Folder 21)
      - General Hume's accounts, 1943-1946, undated (Box 20, Folder 22)
      - German documents, 1944, undated (Box 20, Folder 23)
      - Government publications, undated (Box 20, Folder 24)
      - Italian documents, 1944-1945 (Box 20, Folder 25)
      - Personal statements, 1944-1945, undated (Box 20, Folder 26)
      - Radio transcripts, 1943-1944 (Box 20, Folder 27)
      - Reunion, 1947, undated (Box 20, Folder 28)
  - Manuscripts, Fine Arts and Archives [subcommission of the Allied Military Government in Italy]
    - American Defense-Harvard Group [lists of monuments], 1943 (Box 21, Folder 29)
    - Austria, 1945 (Box 21, Folder 30)
    - "Civil Affairs Handbook, Italy, Section 17: Supplement on Cultural Institutions", 1944
      See: box 53, folder 3
    - Correspondence
      - Official, 1943-1960, undated (Box 21, Folder 31 - 37)
      - Personal [mostly letters of praise for Keller's art rescue efforts], 1944-1945 (Box 21, Folder 38)
    - "Duties of a Fine Arts Officer" [personal account by Keller], 1946, 1948, undated (Box 22, Folder 39)
    - "Field Protection of Objects of Art and Archives", 1944 (Box 22, Folder 40)
    - Italian documents, 1942, 1945, undated (Box 22, Folder 41)
    - Preservation and restoration policies, 1944-1946 (Box 22, Folder 42 - 43)
    - Preservation signs
      - English, undated (Box 22, Folder 44)
      - German, undated (Box 22, Folder 45)
      - Italian, undated (Box 22, Folder 46)
    - Protected artworks [lists], 1943-1944, undated (Box 22, Folder 47)
    - Protected monuments [lists], 1943-1945, undated (Box 22, Folder 48)
    - "Reconstruction Goes Forward in Italy" [Radio interview with Keller and Theodore Sizer], 1946 (Box 22, Folder 49)
    - Reports
      - Final, 1945-1946 (Box 23, Folder 50 - 52)
      - Monthly, 1944-1945 (Box 23, Folder 53)
      - Situation, 1944 (Box 23, Folder 54)
      - Repositories [lists of museum objects removed to safer locations], 1943-1945, undated (Box 23, Folder 55)
      - "Sectional History - Fine Arts" [draft and final], 1956, undated (Box 23, Folder 56)
  - Memorabilia, 1945 (Box 23, Folder 57)
  - Notebooks, 1943-1945, undated (Box 24, Folder 58 - 60)
  - Photographs
    - Envelopes [positives, n.d.]
      - "Alto Adige" (Box 25, Folder 61 - 63)
      - "Alto Adige, 1945" (Box 25, Folder 64)
      - "Alto Adige, Campo Tures" (Box 25, Folder 65)
      - "Alto Adige, July 4, 1945, Merano, [illeg]" (Box 25, Folder 66)
      - "Amalfi" (Box 25, Folder 67)
      - "Anzio" (Box 25, Folder 68 - 73)
      - "Anzio, Nettano" (Box 25, Folder 74 - 75)
      - "Aprilia, Anzio area, tobacco factory" (Box 25, Folder 76)
      - "Barga, Florence, Fourth Corps" (Box 25, Folder 77)
      - "Bay of Naples, Capri" (Box 26, Folder 78)
      - "Bologna area" (Box 26, Folder 79)
      - "Bologna, Bill Mauldin" (Box 26, Folder 80)
      - "Campo? Como? Belvio?" (Box 26, Folder 81)
      - "Campo Tures" (Box 26, Folder 82)
      - "Campo Tures, Alto Adige" (Box 26, Folder 83)
      - "Campo Tures, Bolzano, loading train" (Box 26, Folder 84)
      - "Campo Tures, loading train" (Box 26, Folder 85)
      - "Campo Tures, paintings, Castle M[illeg], Col. Langsdorff" (Box 26, Folder 86)
      - "Campo Tures, Primavera, Normelan's Castle" [includes images of Botticelli's Primavera] (Box 26, Folder 87)
      - "Capri" (Box 26, Folder 88 - 90)
      - "Capt. Mackenzie" (Box 26, Folder 91)
      - "Castle Dorensberg, German loot, Lake Garda, cartoon murals" (Box 26, Folder 92)
      - "Charlie-Bronze Star" (Box 26, Folder 93)
      - "Commercial Trades Institute" (Box 27, Folder 94)
      - "Company G officers" (Box 27, Folder 95)
      - "Cosimo" [return of Cosimo di Medici equestrian statue to Florence] (Box 27, Folder 96 - 98)
      - "Cosimo 1st, cutting the wires" (Box 27, Folder 99)
      - "Distribution of food" (Box 27, Folder 100)
      - "Eboli" (Box 27, Folder 101)
      - "EMS Co. G" [includes photos of art deposit at Campo Tures], undated (Box 27, Folder 102)
      - "Engineering?" (Box 27, Folder 103)
      - "Engineering, north of Florence" (Box 27, Folder 104)
      - "Fine Arts train, Bolzano, etc." (Box 27, Folder 105)
      - "Florence" [Allied Military Government art return ceremony] (Box 27, Folder 106)
      - "Florence" [damage to Uffizi Gallery, fresco restoration] (Box 27, Folder 107 - 108)
      - "Florence" (Box 28, Folder 109 - 111)
      - "Florence and other" (Box 28, Folder 112)
      - "Florence, the David, etc." (Box 28, Folder 113)
      - "Florence, San Minato?" (Box 28, Folder 114)
      - "Food" (Box 28, Folder 115)
      - "Fourth Corps" (Box 28, Folder 116)
      - "Fourth Corps ceremony" (Box 28, Folder 117)
      - "Frank, Toscai, food" (Box 28, Folder 118)
      - "Gardella, Gen. Hume, McMillan" (Box 28, Folder 119)
      - "German" (Box 28, Folder 120 - 124)
      - "German and Italian photos" (Box 29, Folder 125)
      - "German? Girl photos, NOT OURS" (Box 29, Folder 126)
      - "German horse races" (Box 29, Folder 127)
      - "German, Lake Garda, Italians" (Box 29, Folder 128)
      - "German, McMillan, Lt. N[illeg]" (Box 29, Folder 129)
      - "German pictures" (Box 29, Folder 130 - 131)
      - "German, skis" (Box 29, Folder 132)
      - "Girls, German soldiers" (Box 29, Folder 133)
      - "HQ Group" (Box 29, Folder 134)
      - "Hume, Bologna" (Box 29, Folder 135)
      - "Italian" (Box 29, Folder 136)
      - "Italian "Air" (Box 29, Folder 137)
      - "Lake Como, Bolgna" (Box 29, Folder 138)
      - "Leghorn?" (Box 29, Folder 139)
      - "Leghorn, San Rossore, the King's estate" (Box 29, Folder 140)
      - "Lizzano in Bel[illeg], Pistoia" (Box 29, Folder 141)
      - "Lt. Wolford's prints" (Box 29, Folder 142)
      - "Lucca, Pisa" (Box 29, Folder 143)
      - "Massa, Tess Potter, Capt. Keeney, Cosimo" (Box 30, Folder 144)
      - "Milan" (Box 30, Folder 145)
      - "Milan, gas station where Mussolini hung" (Box 30, Folder 146)
      - "Milan, San Maria della Grazia" [bomb damage to cathedral facade] (Box 30, Folder 147)
      - "Monterosi, Capranica" (Box 30, Folder 148)
      - "Montedoro [?] up north" (Box 30, Folder 149)
      - "Mussolini, Bruno" (Box 30, Folder 150)
      - "Naples area?" (Box 30, Folder 151)
      - "Naples, Monte Olivetto Church, German cemetery" [documents damage to church, city, restoration efforts] (Box 30, Folder 152)
      - "Naples, Villa Maria" (Box 30, Folder 153)